<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-11-11T13:02:26+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Enda Phelan</title><subtitle>Software Engineer @ Red Hat</subtitle><entry><title type="html">10 Days in Sri Lanka: Ella</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/10-days-in-sri-lanka-ella" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10 Days in Sri Lanka: Ella" /><published>2018-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/10-days-in-sri-lanka-ella</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/10-days-in-sri-lanka-ella">&lt;p&gt;Tucked away in Sri Lanka’s central highlands a town named Ella sits at an elevation of 1,041 metres above sea level. Traditionally this region has been known for its vast tea plantations, which is one of Sri Lanka’s biggest industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days this laidback town attracts backpackers and adventure seekers alike. Stunning natural scenery, a growing food and nightlife scene and the famous Nine Arches Bridge have helped Ella to become a nailed on destination for tourists visiting Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/aFuIOWW.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived in Ella with the intention of staying three nights before moving onto Kandy. On the third day we extended it to five. There were two reasons that influenced our decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Sri Lanka Declares State of Emergency After Mob Attacks on Muslims”&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;span class=&quot;default-color&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The New York Times&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Sri Lanka violence: State of emergency declared over attacks”&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;span class=&quot;default-color&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BBC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Grenade kills one as social media blocked”&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;span class=&quot;default-color&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Western Advocate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Curfew Declared in Kandy District: 200 Sinha  Regiment Soldiers and 1000 Special Task Force Personnel Deployed as  Police Fail to Control Anti-Muslim Violence.”&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;span class=&quot;default-color&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DBSJeyaraj.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah… that was the main reason we kept the anchor down. The violence had not reached Kandy city, but was happening in several smaller towns and villages in the district. Tensions continued to rise and there was every chance that the violence would spill into the city at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully that day never came, and the violence eventually fizzed out. With only 10 days in Sri Lanka this had the potential to spoil what had so farbeen a great trip. We faced a dilemma which meant altering our plans, or risk our safety by heading straight into the eye of the storm. Our love for Ella assured us that our decision to stay an extra two nights and bypass Kandy completely was the correct one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The town itself is very small, so it’s quite easy to get from your hotel room to one of the town’s many saliva inducing restaurants. The town is nice, but has nothing to attract you other than its bars, shops and restaurants. The things that bring people here are scattered around the surrounding countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/V0aQ43G.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A typical Sri Lankan curry. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re able, get out walking. Many of the main attractions are definitely reachable on foot. If you want to go a bit further there are tuk tuks waiting for you on almost every corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/32b8l97.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ella has a much cooler climate than a lot of Sri Lanka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people in our hostel rented a motorbike so they could explore by themselves. They said they encountered the most jaw-dropping views as they just set off in a random direction to see what they would find. Total freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/vy31zjL.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The roads around Ella were being upgraded when we were there&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-we-stayed&quot;&gt;Where we stayed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We came to Ella to see nature, so we decided to stay outside of the town. The 1964 Boutique Hostel ticks that box and more, it’s about a 25 minute bus ride from Ella town with local buses running regularly at a cost of something like €0.20 (I can’t remember the exact price). We walked to the town once and it took about an hour and a half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t consider it “boutique”, there’s barely any WiFi, and the bed was about 6 inches too short, but everything else about this place was great! We tried to extend our stay but with only four bedrooms it filled up easily. The hosts were so nice - they gave us free local tea and cooked amazing homemade Sri Lankan meals. They also had a tuk tuk service to bring us to places the bus didn’t go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At €10/night for a private room, how could you go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-to-do&quot;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many things to do here. Just walking through the tea plantations could take up hours of your life. Time well spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;walking-through-the-tea-plantations&quot;&gt;Walking through the tea plantations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re just glorified hedges that you can drink, yet they look so damn &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. Right behind our hostel (which was outside of the town) we were right beside fields and fields of tea. Going for a morning walk and being greeted with joy from all the workers out picking was one of our favourite things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/fdsFrGs.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The view from behind our hostel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/G2qNIIo.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/rKy7nhh.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/GY5zsfq.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The hostel’s dog took pleasure in showing guests around the plantations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/BcAqJGu.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The workers were always happy to see us coming. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;demodara-nine-arches-bridge&quot;&gt;Demodara Nine Arches Bridge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nine Arches Bridge is a spectacular feat of engineering. 24 metres tall and 91 metres in length, it was constructed during the British colonial-era as part of a railway system that spans the length and breadth of the country. In its day the railway would have been used to mainly transport coffee and tea from the hills to the country’s main shipping ports. These days it welcomes the public too, offering some of the finest views on an extremely slow and packed train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get here you will probably need a map of some kind, as the bridge can’t be seen from the roadside. We used Maps.me for Android, which uses OpenStreetMap data. Unlike Google Maps, OpenStreetMap data is crowdsourced, meaning any person like you or me can contribute to it. The route we chose brought us off the road and through the tea-plantations on a tiny dirt path to the bridge, which had us amazed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/p2RtiGU.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Searching for the Nine Arches Bridge. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a little while walking through the tea maze we came to an opening where a local man started trying to usher us in the opposite direction to the map route, saying “Bridge!” every now and then in an effort to reassure us. We were hesitant, but decided to trust him as there were some other tourists with him, en route to the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He started bringing us a very long and unusual way, through houses until we weren’t really on a path anymore. We cut our losses and turned around in the direction we came from to go back on our original path, ignoring the man’s yells back at us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met that same couple down at the bridge later, so at least he was actually bringing people there. My feeling is that he brings people this way so that he can ask for money when they come back! My advice would be to just ignore these people, use Maps.me and you’ll be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we got to the bridge, we came across a great viewing point with a simple little tea shop, where you can sit and sip on some local tea and wait for one of the five (I think) daily trains to pass. When we got here, a scribbled timetable told us that the next train was two hours away, so we didn’t wait for it. Be sure to check with your hostel before going if you want to catch one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/RgtXfTj.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/x1DJ3yC.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Here’s the tea shop. Minimalism!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/UaokKhg.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This is the spectacular view just below the tea shop!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/M8RDoXC.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;No, I don’t know yer man.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/o54Yl9T.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;From the other end. No, I don’t know yer man.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/zV2HKoK.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/og3ARFv.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In Sri Lanka it’s common to walk along railway lines. The trains are so slow you’ve little chance of being hit!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ravana-falls&quot;&gt;Ravana Falls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Sri Lanka, the name Ella actually means “waterfall”. Standing 25 metres tall, the Ravana Falls is just outside the town. It is also one of the widest waterfalls in the entire country. We walked to these falls from the town. It took us just under two hours, though we took our time and stopped several times along the way to admire the views of the valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/x2xNcwJ.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ravana Falls&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ravanas-cave&quot;&gt;Ravana’s Cave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs. 150-200&lt;/em&gt;. On the way to Ravana Falls, you may first want to make a small detour and head to Ravana’s Cave. According to legend, KIng Rawana used this cave to hide the princess Sita. Even if that much is folklore, excavations undertaken in the cave revealed evidence of human habitation dating back 25,000 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prepare to climb some 650 steps to reach the cave. We enjoyed it, but it’s quite small when you get there so I’m sure many people are left disappointed at spending their money and sweat to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/ybWF8dZ.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;So. Many. Steps…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/P0ro6Rz.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;From inside the cave. Bring a headlamp if you have one!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/dfhliKc.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Getting down will be easier.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 3/4 of the way up to the cave there is a hut selling coconut drinks. We stopped off on our way back down for a rest and to try a King coconut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/R6vgNLB.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The unusual looking King coconut 🥥&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;little-adams-peak&quot;&gt;Little Adam’s Peak&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little Adam’s Peak is a pretty easy hike. It attracts tourists and locals, who come to take in the spectacular 360° views from atop the 1141 metre high summit, which looks down on the valley below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get on the trail leading to the top you must go to the 98 Acres Resort and follow the signs from there. It’s well signposted, you shouldn’t get lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/SJGFVet.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It wasn’t a very clear day when we climbed it, but the views were still amazing!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/Cx7UsPD.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ella Rock as seen from Little Adam’s Peak&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/Q2pmoSh.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I don’t know why, but there were several dogs sleeping at the top&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goodbye Ella, goodbye Sri Lanka! 10 days wasn’t near enough in this country. There were so many places we wanted to fit into our itnerary but just couldn’t, like Udawalewe National Park, Sigiriya and Lipton’s Seat. I guess that just leaves us with good reason to come back 😉!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson we learned from India and Sri Lanka is that slow travel beats fast travel. With that we decided to spend just over two months in Thailand (exceeding our visa and getting a fine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to check out my video, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/E2lfkVyPT-c&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2 Minutes in Sri Lanka&lt;/a&gt; if you haven’t already!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="sri-lanka" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="ella" /><category term="tea" /><category term="bridge" /><category term="nature" /><category term="waterfall" /><summary type="html">Tucked away in Sri Lanka’s central highlands a town named Ella sits at an elevation of 1,041 metres above sea level. Traditionally this region has been known for its vast tea plantations, which is one of Sri Lanka’s biggest industries.

These days this laidback town attracts backpackers and adventure seekers alike. Stunning natural scenery, a growing food and nightlife scene and the famous Nine Arches Bridge have helped Ella to become a nailed on destination for tourists visiting Sri Lanka.



We arrived in Ella with the intention of staying three nights before moving onto Kandy. On the third day we extended it to five. There were two reasons that influenced our decision.


  “Sri Lanka Declares State of Emergency After Mob Attacks on Muslims” - The New York Times



  “Sri Lanka violence: State of emergency declared over attacks” - BBC



  “Grenade kills one as social media blocked” - Western Advocate



  “Curfew Declared in Kandy District: 200 Sinha  Regiment Soldiers and 1000 Special Task Force Personnel Deployed as  Police Fail to Control Anti-Muslim Violence.” - DBSJeyaraj.com


Yeah… that was the main reason we kept the anchor down. The violence had not reached Kandy city, but was happening in several smaller towns and villages in the district. Tensions continued to rise and there was every chance that the violence would spill into the city at any time.

Thankfully that day never came, and the violence eventually fizzed out. With only 10 days in Sri Lanka this had the potential to spoil what had so farbeen a great trip. We faced a dilemma which meant altering our plans, or risk our safety by heading straight into the eye of the storm. Our love for Ella assured us that our decision to stay an extra two nights and bypass Kandy completely was the correct one.

Getting around

The town itself is very small, so it’s quite easy to get from your hotel room to one of the town’s many saliva inducing restaurants. The town is nice, but has nothing to attract you other than its bars, shops and restaurants. The things that bring people here are scattered around the surrounding countryside.


A typical Sri Lankan curry. 📸 by Sarah

If you’re able, get out walking. Many of the main attractions are definitely reachable on foot. If you want to go a bit further there are tuk tuks waiting for you on almost every corner.


Ella has a much cooler climate than a lot of Sri Lanka

Some people in our hostel rented a motorbike so they could explore by themselves. They said they encountered the most jaw-dropping views as they just set off in a random direction to see what they would find. Total freedom.


The roads around Ella were being upgraded when we were there

Where we stayed

We came to Ella to see nature, so we decided to stay outside of the town. The 1964 Boutique Hostel ticks that box and more, it’s about a 25 minute bus ride from Ella town with local buses running regularly at a cost of something like €0.20 (I can’t remember the exact price). We walked to the town once and it took about an hour and a half.

I wouldn’t consider it “boutique”, there’s barely any WiFi, and the bed was about 6 inches too short, but everything else about this place was great! We tried to extend our stay but with only four bedrooms it filled up easily. The hosts were so nice - they gave us free local tea and cooked amazing homemade Sri Lankan meals. They also had a tuk tuk service to bring us to places the bus didn’t go!

At €10/night for a private room, how could you go wrong?

Things to do

There are so many things to do here. Just walking through the tea plantations could take up hours of your life. Time well spent.

Walking through the tea plantations

They’re just glorified hedges that you can drink, yet they look so damn good. Right behind our hostel (which was outside of the town) we were right beside fields and fields of tea. Going for a morning walk and being greeted with joy from all the workers out picking was one of our favourite things to do.


The view from behind our hostel






The hostel’s dog took pleasure in showing guests around the plantations


The workers were always happy to see us coming. 📸 by Sarah

Demodara Nine Arches Bridge

The Nine Arches Bridge is a spectacular feat of engineering. 24 metres tall and 91 metres in length, it was constructed during the British colonial-era as part of a railway system that spans the length and breadth of the country. In its day the railway would have been used to mainly transport coffee and tea from the hills to the country’s main shipping ports. These days it welcomes the public too, offering some of the finest views on an extremely slow and packed train.

To get here you will probably need a map of some kind, as the bridge can’t be seen from the roadside. We used Maps.me for Android, which uses OpenStreetMap data. Unlike Google Maps, OpenStreetMap data is crowdsourced, meaning any person like you or me can contribute to it. The route we chose brought us off the road and through the tea-plantations on a tiny dirt path to the bridge, which had us amazed.


Searching for the Nine Arches Bridge. 📸 by Sarah

After a little while walking through the tea maze we came to an opening where a local man started trying to usher us in the opposite direction to the map route, saying “Bridge!” every now and then in an effort to reassure us. We were hesitant, but decided to trust him as there were some other tourists with him, en route to the bridge.

He started bringing us a very long and unusual way, through houses until we weren’t really on a path anymore. We cut our losses and turned around in the direction we came from to go back on our original path, ignoring the man’s yells back at us.

We met that same couple down at the bridge later, so at least he was actually bringing people there. My feeling is that he brings people this way so that he can ask for money when they come back! My advice would be to just ignore these people, use Maps.me and you’ll be fine.

Before we got to the bridge, we came across a great viewing point with a simple little tea shop, where you can sit and sip on some local tea and wait for one of the five (I think) daily trains to pass. When we got here, a scribbled timetable told us that the next train was two hours away, so we didn’t wait for it. Be sure to check with your hostel before going if you want to catch one!




Here’s the tea shop. Minimalism!


This is the spectacular view just below the tea shop!


No, I don’t know yer man.


From the other end. No, I don’t know yer man.




In Sri Lanka it’s common to walk along railway lines. The trains are so slow you’ve little chance of being hit!

Ravana Falls

In Sri Lanka, the name Ella actually means “waterfall”. Standing 25 metres tall, the Ravana Falls is just outside the town. It is also one of the widest waterfalls in the entire country. We walked to these falls from the town. It took us just under two hours, though we took our time and stopped several times along the way to admire the views of the valley.


Ravana Falls

Ravana’s Cave

Entry: Rs. 150-200. On the way to Ravana Falls, you may first want to make a small detour and head to Ravana’s Cave. According to legend, KIng Rawana used this cave to hide the princess Sita. Even if that much is folklore, excavations undertaken in the cave revealed evidence of human habitation dating back 25,000 years!

Prepare to climb some 650 steps to reach the cave. We enjoyed it, but it’s quite small when you get there so I’m sure many people are left disappointed at spending their money and sweat to see it.


So. Many. Steps…


From inside the cave. Bring a headlamp if you have one!


Getting down will be easier.

About 3/4 of the way up to the cave there is a hut selling coconut drinks. We stopped off on our way back down for a rest and to try a King coconut.


The unusual looking King coconut 🥥

Little Adam’s Peak

Little Adam’s Peak is a pretty easy hike. It attracts tourists and locals, who come to take in the spectacular 360° views from atop the 1141 metre high summit, which looks down on the valley below.

To get on the trail leading to the top you must go to the 98 Acres Resort and follow the signs from there. It’s well signposted, you shouldn’t get lost.


It wasn’t a very clear day when we climbed it, but the views were still amazing!


Ella Rock as seen from Little Adam’s Peak


I don’t know why, but there were several dogs sleeping at the top

Moving on

Goodbye Ella, goodbye Sri Lanka! 10 days wasn’t near enough in this country. There were so many places we wanted to fit into our itnerary but just couldn’t, like Udawalewe National Park, Sigiriya and Lipton’s Seat. I guess that just leaves us with good reason to come back 😉!

The lesson we learned from India and Sri Lanka is that slow travel beats fast travel. With that we decided to spend just over two months in Thailand (exceeding our visa and getting a fine).

Be sure to check out my video, 2 Minutes in Sri Lanka if you haven’t already!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000M8RDoXC.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">10 Days in Sri Lanka: Unawatuna &amp;amp; Galle Fort</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/10-days-in-sri-lanka-unawatuna-and-galle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10 Days in Sri Lanka: Unawatuna &amp; Galle Fort" /><published>2018-09-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/10-days-in-sri-lanka-unawatuna-and-galle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/10-days-in-sri-lanka-unawatuna-and-galle">&lt;p&gt;Sri Lanka only came on our radar when we were booking our flight from India to Thailand. We would have to catch a connecting flight in Colombo, Sri Lanka’s capital anyway so we just decided to stretch the stopover to 10 days and see a bit of India’s teardrop. It’s a pity we didn’t research it a bit more before booking the tickets as we would have stayed a lot longer than 10 days!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a short flight we were on the ground again and walking through Colombo Airport in search of a booth to buy some local SIM cards and reconnect to the grid. Prior research told us that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dialog.lk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dialog&lt;/a&gt; is the best network for 4G coverage, which is all we really cared about when it came to choosing a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that the next thing to do was find an ATM and withdraw some rupees. You know the way ATMs normally give you back your card before producing the cash? The one I used must have missed that day in ATM University, so I ended up leaving my travel card in the ATM and didn’t realise until several hours later when there was over 120 kilometres of highway between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good job I had opened an account with &lt;a href=&quot;https://n26.com/en-eu/bank-account&quot;&gt;N26&lt;/a&gt; before leaving. I literally just had to open their app on my phone and block all withdrawals and transactions with the tap of a button. If you’re in the EU you should definitely consider getting an N26 Black card if you are going to be abroad for a long time. It’s &lt;del&gt;€5.90/month&lt;/del&gt; &lt;strong&gt;€9.90/month&lt;/strong&gt; but you will make up that cost with fee-free payments and withdrawals and an Allianz insurance package! This is not an ad, it’s just really really good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unawatuna&quot;&gt;Unawatuna&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only 10 days to see the country we decided not to stay in Colombo, instead heading straight from the airport to Unawatuna on the southwest coast. This may be a small town but it is one of Sri Lanka’s biggest tourist destinations, best known for its long and curving golden beach, shielded by palm trees, restaurants and resorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/a3pMPLI.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/ERXKW3Q.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/eGGXazz.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/1C4NCm0.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-here&quot;&gt;Getting here&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three feasible ways for us to get from the airport to our hostel in Unawatuna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bus&quot;&gt;Bus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to take the bus here’s what you need to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bus No. 187&lt;/strong&gt; from the airport bus station to Colombo Fort. Buses run &lt;strong&gt;every 30 minutes&lt;/strong&gt; between 05:30 and 18:30. The journey should take around &lt;strong&gt;45 minutes&lt;/strong&gt;, at a cost of &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 110 (€0.58)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From here, take &lt;strong&gt;Bus No. 2&lt;/strong&gt; to Matara (getting off at Galle). Buses run &lt;strong&gt;every 30 minutes&lt;/strong&gt; between 05:00 and 20:00. It should take around &lt;strong&gt;3 hours&lt;/strong&gt;. It costs &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 490 (€2.58)&lt;/strong&gt; to Matara so it should be a little bit less to Galle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a tuk tuk from Galle to Unawatuna. This should take around &lt;strong&gt;15 minutes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;train&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Train&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bus No. 187&lt;/strong&gt; from the airport bus station to Colombo Fort. Buses run &lt;strong&gt;every 30 minutes&lt;/strong&gt; between 05:30 and 18:30. The journey should take around &lt;strong&gt;45 minutes&lt;/strong&gt;, at a cost of &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 110 (€0.58)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get the train from Colombo Fort to Galle. There are &lt;strong&gt;10 trains per day&lt;/strong&gt;, from 06:55 to 19:30. The journey should take a little over &lt;strong&gt;3 hours&lt;/strong&gt; (but often more). A 3rd class ticket cost &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 100 (€0.53)&lt;/strong&gt;, and 2nd class tickets are &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 180 (€0.95)&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://slr.malindaprasad.com/index.php?from=FOT&amp;amp;to=GLE&quot;&gt;Full Schedule&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a tuk tuk from Galle to Unawatuna. This should take around &lt;strong&gt;15 minutes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;car-rental-with-driver&quot;&gt;Car rental with driver&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having just landed in the country we didn’t have a clue about what train or bus to take. We went to the tourist information desk in the airport and they recommended getting a private car with a driver. We decided to go with this as it was the easiest option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were quoted &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 60,000 (€80)&lt;/strong&gt; for the journey. We were hesitant about parting with so much of our money until we met someone from our plane who was travelling a little bit further south along the same route to Mirissa so we split the fare three ways. We ended up paying &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 5,000 (€26) each&lt;/strong&gt;…which wasn’t as bad, but it is still extremely expensive for Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey was great though, and somewhat worth the price for the comfort and convenience. It only took us about &lt;strong&gt;2 hours&lt;/strong&gt; and the driver brought us right to the door of our hostel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;walking&quot;&gt;Walking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get to Unawatuna you can easily walk everywhere. I would recommend staying near the beach though as you’ll never need to walk any longer than 10 minutes! Our hostel was about a 30 minute walk from the beach. Most of this walk is along the A2 Highway that connects Colombo to the south of the country. This is a really busy highway with huge lorries and buses thundering past at every hour - I wouldn’t advise walking on it at night as it’s a bit dangerous…though we did once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tuk-tuk&quot;&gt;Tuk tuk&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah the good ol’ trusty tuk tuk. Well, I wouldn’t go that far. Expect to pay &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 50-60 (€0.60) per kilometre&lt;/strong&gt; in Unawatuna and most places in the country. Rarely will you find a metered taxi - it’s “broken”. Of course, they will try and charge you much more than this, but bargain, bargain hard. Walk away and they will drop their price, guaranteed. They’re sound though, just trying their luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/3rcvqYS.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;There’s no better way to see the world than from the back of a tuk tuk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;places-to-eat&quot;&gt;Places to eat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one place in Unawatuna you &lt;em&gt;must try&lt;/em&gt;! I couldn’t find it online, it’s not on Google Maps and I don’t think it has a name. You can find it on &lt;strong&gt;Welle Dewayala road&lt;/strong&gt; (the road connecting the highway to Unawatuna beach) on your right as you walk towards the beach. They have one dish and they make it well. &lt;strong&gt;Kottu Roti&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s a tiny place with only two or three tables, so you will be lucky to get a seat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/oj7N4mY.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Our first taste of a Kottu Roti. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/FR7e9xO.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;If you see this on the wall outside you’ve come to the right place!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;galle-fort&quot;&gt;Galle Fort&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made a day-trip from Unawatuna to Galle, to see the famous Galle Fort. Built by the Portuguese in 1588, it remained under their control until 1640, when the Dutch captured it. They then proceeded to extensively fortify it and make it their headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.saltinourhair.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/galle-dutch-fort-sri-lanka-map.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Galle Fort. Image from &lt;a href=&quot;https://saltinourhair.com/sri-lanka/galle-fort/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Salt in our Hair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-around-1&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get to the main gate there will be several tuk tuk drivers waiting to tell you “it’s too big to walk, I will bring you around”. Don’t listen to them, it’s easy to walk around here and it’s the most fun thing about this place. To me there are no stand out attractions in Galle Fort. The collective experience of taking the long way around and coming across the attractions in your own time is what makes visiting this place so enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/sOCKfVN.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The clock tower is one of the first things you will see when you arrive&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/m6xFVSx.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Galle Fort is a popular place for diving&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/4XuQhkM.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Galle Lighthouse undergoing some conservation work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/VnpOm7A.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The entire fort is extremely well kept&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/kHT1kUQ.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Dutch Reformed Church&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/ZqOcaKm.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The best way to explore this place is by foot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/8vOSisi.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Galle Fort as viewed from Dharmapala Park&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/UsyNhHb.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Horses grazing in Dharmapala Park&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two days in Unawatuna and Galle really isn’t enough, but we only had 10 days so we couldn’t stay any longer. Next we headed to the centre of the country to a small town called Ella, high up in the mountains. Its stunning views, waterfalls, tea plantations and hiking opportunities have made this one of Sri Lanka’s top tourist destinations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="sri-lanka" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="unawatuna" /><category term="galle" /><category term="fort" /><category term="church" /><category term="beach" /><category term="food" /><summary type="html">Sri Lanka only came on our radar when we were booking our flight from India to Thailand. We would have to catch a connecting flight in Colombo, Sri Lanka’s capital anyway so we just decided to stretch the stopover to 10 days and see a bit of India’s teardrop. It’s a pity we didn’t research it a bit more before booking the tickets as we would have stayed a lot longer than 10 days!

After a short flight we were on the ground again and walking through Colombo Airport in search of a booth to buy some local SIM cards and reconnect to the grid. Prior research told us that Dialog is the best network for 4G coverage, which is all we really cared about when it came to choosing a network.

After that the next thing to do was find an ATM and withdraw some rupees. You know the way ATMs normally give you back your card before producing the cash? The one I used must have missed that day in ATM University, so I ended up leaving my travel card in the ATM and didn’t realise until several hours later when there was over 120 kilometres of highway between us.

Good job I had opened an account with N26 before leaving. I literally just had to open their app on my phone and block all withdrawals and transactions with the tap of a button. If you’re in the EU you should definitely consider getting an N26 Black card if you are going to be abroad for a long time. It’s €5.90/month €9.90/month but you will make up that cost with fee-free payments and withdrawals and an Allianz insurance package! This is not an ad, it’s just really really good.

Unawatuna

With only 10 days to see the country we decided not to stay in Colombo, instead heading straight from the airport to Unawatuna on the southwest coast. This may be a small town but it is one of Sri Lanka’s biggest tourist destinations, best known for its long and curving golden beach, shielded by palm trees, restaurants and resorts.









Getting here

There were three feasible ways for us to get from the airport to our hostel in Unawatuna.

Bus

If you want to take the bus here’s what you need to do.


  Bus No. 187 from the airport bus station to Colombo Fort. Buses run every 30 minutes between 05:30 and 18:30. The journey should take around 45 minutes, at a cost of Rs. 110 (€0.58).
  From here, take Bus No. 2 to Matara (getting off at Galle). Buses run every 30 minutes between 05:00 and 20:00. It should take around 3 hours. It costs Rs. 490 (€2.58) to Matara so it should be a little bit less to Galle.
  Get a tuk tuk from Galle to Unawatuna. This should take around 15 minutes.


Train


  Bus No. 187 from the airport bus station to Colombo Fort. Buses run every 30 minutes between 05:30 and 18:30. The journey should take around 45 minutes, at a cost of Rs. 110 (€0.58).
  Get the train from Colombo Fort to Galle. There are 10 trains per day, from 06:55 to 19:30. The journey should take a little over 3 hours (but often more). A 3rd class ticket cost Rs. 100 (€0.53), and 2nd class tickets are Rs. 180 (€0.95). Full Schedule.
  Get a tuk tuk from Galle to Unawatuna. This should take around 15 minutes.


Car rental with driver

Having just landed in the country we didn’t have a clue about what train or bus to take. We went to the tourist information desk in the airport and they recommended getting a private car with a driver. We decided to go with this as it was the easiest option.

We were quoted Rs. 60,000 (€80) for the journey. We were hesitant about parting with so much of our money until we met someone from our plane who was travelling a little bit further south along the same route to Mirissa so we split the fare three ways. We ended up paying Rs. 5,000 (€26) each…which wasn’t as bad, but it is still extremely expensive for Sri Lanka.

The journey was great though, and somewhat worth the price for the comfort and convenience. It only took us about 2 hours and the driver brought us right to the door of our hostel!

Getting around

Walking

Once you get to Unawatuna you can easily walk everywhere. I would recommend staying near the beach though as you’ll never need to walk any longer than 10 minutes! Our hostel was about a 30 minute walk from the beach. Most of this walk is along the A2 Highway that connects Colombo to the south of the country. This is a really busy highway with huge lorries and buses thundering past at every hour - I wouldn’t advise walking on it at night as it’s a bit dangerous…though we did once.

Tuk tuk

Ah the good ol’ trusty tuk tuk. Well, I wouldn’t go that far. Expect to pay Rs. 50-60 (€0.60) per kilometre in Unawatuna and most places in the country. Rarely will you find a metered taxi - it’s “broken”. Of course, they will try and charge you much more than this, but bargain, bargain hard. Walk away and they will drop their price, guaranteed. They’re sound though, just trying their luck.


There’s no better way to see the world than from the back of a tuk tuk

Places to eat

There is one place in Unawatuna you must try! I couldn’t find it online, it’s not on Google Maps and I don’t think it has a name. You can find it on Welle Dewayala road (the road connecting the highway to Unawatuna beach) on your right as you walk towards the beach. They have one dish and they make it well. Kottu Roti. It’s a tiny place with only two or three tables, so you will be lucky to get a seat!


Our first taste of a Kottu Roti. 📸 by Sarah


If you see this on the wall outside you’ve come to the right place!

Galle Fort

We made a day-trip from Unawatuna to Galle, to see the famous Galle Fort. Built by the Portuguese in 1588, it remained under their control until 1640, when the Dutch captured it. They then proceeded to extensively fortify it and make it their headquarters.


Galle Fort. Image from Salt in our Hair

Getting around

When you get to the main gate there will be several tuk tuk drivers waiting to tell you “it’s too big to walk, I will bring you around”. Don’t listen to them, it’s easy to walk around here and it’s the most fun thing about this place. To me there are no stand out attractions in Galle Fort. The collective experience of taking the long way around and coming across the attractions in your own time is what makes visiting this place so enjoyable.


The clock tower is one of the first things you will see when you arrive


Galle Fort is a popular place for diving


Galle Lighthouse undergoing some conservation work


The entire fort is extremely well kept


Dutch Reformed Church


The best way to explore this place is by foot


Galle Fort as viewed from Dharmapala Park


Horses grazing in Dharmapala Park

Moving on

Two days in Unawatuna and Galle really isn’t enough, but we only had 10 days so we couldn’t stay any longer. Next we headed to the centre of the country to a small town called Ella, high up in the mountains. Its stunning views, waterfalls, tea plantations and hiking opportunities have made this one of Sri Lanka’s top tourist destinations.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000kHT1kUQ.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2 Minutes in Sri Lanka</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/2-minutes-in-sri-lanka" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2 Minutes in Sri Lanka" /><published>2018-08-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/2-minutes-in-sri-lanka</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/sri-lanka/2-minutes-in-sri-lanka">&lt;p&gt;Here’s a short highlight video of our 10 day trip to Sri Lanka. Blog series coming soon ✍ Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-iframe post-yt&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;440&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/E2lfkVyPT-c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="sri-lanka" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="video" /><category term="highlights" /><category term="YouTube" /><summary type="html">Here’s a short highlight video of our 10 day trip to Sri Lanka. Blog series coming soon ✍ Enjoy!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000bWTo3m1.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Minute in India</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/one-minute-in-india" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Minute in India" /><published>2018-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/india/one-minute-in-india</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/one-minute-in-india">&lt;p&gt;If you are considering a visit to India, do it. It’s a massive melting pot of different people, cultures, landscapes and food so there is literally plenty of things and places to suit everybody’s interests. Yes at times it will challenging, but in the end it will be an extremely rewarding experience in which you will learn so much. We spent one month here and loved &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; second. Read my &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/india&quot;&gt;other posts&lt;/a&gt; and see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a little montage I put together showing some of the highlights. Enjoy! 📽&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-iframe post-yt&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;440&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VbrrzrkrjxA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="india" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="video" /><category term="highlights" /><category term="YouTube" /><summary type="html">If you are considering a visit to India, do it. It’s a massive melting pot of different people, cultures, landscapes and food so there is literally plenty of things and places to suit everybody’s interests. Yes at times it will challenging, but in the end it will be an extremely rewarding experience in which you will learn so much. We spent one month here and loved every second. Read my other posts and see why.

Here’s a little montage I put together showing some of the highlights. Enjoy! 📽</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000YriqAQH.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Month in India: Kerala</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-kerala" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Month in India: Kerala" /><published>2018-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-kerala</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-kerala">&lt;p&gt;Kerala. God’s Own Country. Actually that title belongs to the Wicklow Mountains in Ireland but we’ll forgive them for that one. Just this once. After all, there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_places_called_Venice_of_North&quot;&gt;40 Venice of the Norths&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris_of_the_East&quot;&gt;24 Paris of the Easts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighth_Wonder_of_the_World&quot;&gt;50 Eighth Wonders of the World&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/God%27s_Own_Country&quot;&gt;another six places&lt;/a&gt; in the world that God himself calls his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waterfalls, beaches, rainforests, national parks, mountains, picture-perfect tea plantations and a network of freshwater rivers, canals, lakes and lagoons collectively known as the “Kerala Backwaters” (and Venice of the East). I can see why God likes Kerala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly we didn’t see the majority of what I just listed. For the final leg of the trip we decided to slow it right down in a country that doesn’t know the meaning of the word “slow” - and focus our adventures on two places: Kochi and Kovalam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We came to this decision while scanning over the itinerary we had created, which revealed a packed schedule - in transit every two or three days and spending over 50 hours sitting, standing or laying in a train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kochi&quot;&gt;Kochi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kochi is an ancient port city in south-central Kerala, founded way back in the 14th century. It has a long history of trading with many countries from all over the Old World, including Portugal, Netherlands, China and Japan, which has over time created a distinct cosmopolitan culture unlike any other place in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being well known around the world from of its valuable spice trade industry was probably a big reason why the Portuguese chose it as their gateway to colonisation in India, with occupation beginning in 1503. To this day you can still see the effects of colonisation in the old town, with European influences on architecture, art and religion visible everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’ll probably want to stay in or near Fort Kochi (also referred to as the old town or Old Kochi). This is where most of the tourist attractions and some of the best restaurants are found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you heed my advice you’ll find that most places can easily be reached on foot. If you’re not into walking, cycling is a great way to get around the old town as the roads are pretty calm and most journeys should take no longer than 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/YriqAQH.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A gorgeous little street in Old Kochi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a local bus network in Kochi that is apparently very good, but the tuk tuks are so cheap and convenient we just used them whenever we needed to go on a longer journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-do&quot;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could probably visit most of the top attractions Fort Kochi has in a day. It’s worth staying a bit longer as the town itself has a nice vibe and there’s a great restaurant scene. Here are the highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;elephant-festival&quot;&gt;Elephant Festival&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. The day we arrived to Kochi our host told us about an elephant festival that would be happening nearby at 17:00. I don’t think this is an everyday occurrence, we just got lucky with the day we arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were excited with what we saw as this was our first time seeing elephants this close up and outside of a zoo. There was a short parade followed by traditional music and a ritual which ended with a blessing of the elephants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/hsUhWIF.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly the legs of these gentle giants were chained together and all three of them had a couple of men sitting or standing on their backs. At this time we weren’t aware of how serious and horrible elephant cruelty is in India and many other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back with this new information the whole event seemed a bit cruel and unfair. Who knows, maybe these ones were well cared for but evidence would suggest otherwise. Watch the video below and decide on the ethicality of such an event for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-iframe post-yt&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bfGZpaXEZvE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chinese-fishing-nets&quot;&gt;Chinese Fishing Nets&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. If you do a Google Image search for &lt;em&gt;Kochi&lt;/em&gt; the most frequent image you will see as you scroll down is the iconic Chinese Fishing Nets at Fort Kochi Beach. Below is an example I grabbed from Google. Beautiful isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-A3n8ATaRc6Q/VRF5TTOkNNI/AAAAAAAABh8/fQhPQCV0Rbw/s1600/Fortkochi%2C%2BChines%2Bnet.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Expectation. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keralatrips.co.in/2015/04/2015-to-be-visit-kerala-year.html&quot;&gt;Kerala Trips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you hope to see the Chinese Fishing Nets looking remotely like this come at sunset. We went in the early afternoon and they were the pretty ugly, with rubbish strewn everywhere around them and that typical smell you get near a fish market. I’ll show you my pic but look away if you still want to go as it might turn you off!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/tBQ2QuY.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reality. Source: Me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;santa-cruz-cathedral-basilica&quot;&gt;Santa Cruz Cathedral Basilica&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. 2.3% of the population identifies as Christian, making it the third most followed religion in India, behind Hinduism (80%) and Islam (14%). It’s believed that Christianity was first introduced to India by Thomas the Apostle in 52 AD, but it began to spread more effectively in the 16th century when the Portuguese came and colonised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/059K74t.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Santa Cruz Cathedral Basilica&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;indo-portuguese-museum&quot;&gt;Indo-Portuguese Museum&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs. 25&lt;/em&gt;. Established to showcase the Portuguese influence on Kochi and the surrounding areas, this is a small museum displaying mostly Christian relics and artefacts. We didn’t find it particularly interesting and didn’t stay long. It could be something to do if you have a lot of time to spare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;st-francis-church&quot;&gt;St. Francis Church&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. To look at, it’s just an ordinary no frills old church, badly in need of some maintenance, but looks don’t write history. Built in 1503, this is the oldest European church in India. Over the years it has changed hands several times between the Portuguese, Dutch and British as they battled for control over the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/PzyoBu4.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;St. Francis Church. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The explorer Vasco de Gama, who discovered the sea route from Europe to India in 1498, was buried here for 14 years before his remains were returned to Portugal. It’s historical and cultural significance was marked in 1923 when it was declared a protected monument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sitar-and-tabla-performance&quot;&gt;Sitar and Tabla Performance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs. 200&lt;/em&gt;. A flyer advertising a sitar and tabla performance in Kerala Kathakali Centre caught our eye as we wandered the quaint streets of Old Kochi so we decided to check it out. We had absolutely no idea what a sitar and tabla were or what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/LHL5Nbh.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Tablaist (left) and sitarist mid-performance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We loved it. The performance began at 20:00 and consisted of two talented musicians - one on sitar and the other on tabla - playing an intimate one hour set of hypnotising instrumental music. I think the small audience was in a trance as the only noises in the entire hour came from those beautiful instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/TcKy0e7.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;An old cannon in Vasco de Gama Square&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/YfRHfh6.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A local park that becomes a cricket stadium in the evenings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;places-to-eat&quot;&gt;Places to eat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kochi has some mouth-wateringly good restaurants 🤤.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;qissa-café&quot;&gt;Qissa Café&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit, we’re not fan the biggest fans of an Indian breakfast. We always ended up getting some of our favourite Western breakfasts which can be easily found in tourist areas. It’s been five months and I still have dreams about the breakfast we had in Qissa.&lt;br /&gt;
📍 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/UAQPCEhAGCs&quot;&gt;Near Private Bus Terminal, 18, KB Jacob Rd, Fort Kochi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/CG1cFVg.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In brunch heaven at Qissa Café. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;farmers-café&quot;&gt;Farmer’s Café&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We came here for dinner one night and shared a harbour masala (fish cooked in spicy gravy) and it was so so good. No pics because it was eaten so fast.
&lt;br /&gt;📍 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/pXLVxPTSXu12&quot;&gt;682001, Rids Dale road, Next to the post office, Fort Kochi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kovalam&quot;&gt;Kovalam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t plan to do too much in Kovalam. Besides, there’s not really anything to do apart from chill at the beach which is exactly what we wanted. I was still trying to go from pale to slightly less pale and five days in sunny Kovalam is a good place to do just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also a quick 20 minute drive to Trivandrum Airport, where we were due to fly to Sri Lanka from on March 6th. This tipped the balance in favour of Kovalam when we were deciding where to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-around-1&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kovalam is a small town of about 8,000. As the only things of interest to tourists are the beach and lighthouse you should be able to reach most places within a five minute walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to find some cheaper local restaurants or an ATM (there aren’t any on the tourist strip oddly enough) you will need to venture a couple of streets back up a steep hill, which could take you 15 minutes or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-do-1&quot;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than lounging on the beach, browsing the small gift shops and dining, there’s not a whole lot to do here, which is exactly what attracts people. It’s a popular holiday destination where foreign and domestic tourists as well as locals come and enjoy the beach, seafood and sunshine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kovalam-beach&quot;&gt;Kovalam Beach&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. Poular with locals, this is a really nice beach but it is always &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; busy, so if you’re looking for something a bit more peaceful you should head back to Goa. We had a great time here sunbathing on the beach and cooling off in the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/BLUwAci.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Locals flock to Kovalam Beach for sunset. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lighthouse-beach&quot;&gt;Lighthouse Beach&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. This beach sits adjacent to Kovalam Beach and is very popular with foreign tourists, separated only by a tiny strip of land and rocks. It gets its name from Vizhinjam lighthouse, which sits elevated on a hill at the south end looking down on the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/qHIn1uX.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Lighthouse Beach in the morning. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/3hnZLjE.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Breakfast with a view. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vizhinjam-lighthouse&quot;&gt;Vizhinjam Lighthouse&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs. 25&lt;/em&gt;. Towering above the coconut palm trees at a height of 36 metres, this picturesque and iconic landmark dominates the Kovalam skyline. If you ask a kid to draw a lighthouse it would probably look just like this. It’s open to visitors, but at the time we were here it was closed for renovations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/B7vqEuN.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Vizhinjam Lighthouse. 📸 by Sarah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;अलविदा. गुडबाय. വിട … Goodbye India! What an experience. What a month. What a country. Our only regret is that we didn’t give it enough time. Kerala alone deserves at least a couple of weeks if you want to explore all it has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be our final destination in India, but there’s still a few more posts to come. Next week (or the week after) I’ll show you a one minute highlights video that I made. See you then 😉.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="india" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="kerala" /><category term="beach" /><category term="elephant" /><category term="kochi" /><category term="kovalam" /><summary type="html">Kerala. God’s Own Country. Actually that title belongs to the Wicklow Mountains in Ireland but we’ll forgive them for that one. Just this once. After all, there are 40 Venice of the Norths, 24 Paris of the Easts, 50 Eighth Wonders of the World and another six places in the world that God himself calls his own.

Waterfalls, beaches, rainforests, national parks, mountains, picture-perfect tea plantations and a network of freshwater rivers, canals, lakes and lagoons collectively known as the “Kerala Backwaters” (and Venice of the East). I can see why God likes Kerala.

Sadly we didn’t see the majority of what I just listed. For the final leg of the trip we decided to slow it right down in a country that doesn’t know the meaning of the word “slow” - and focus our adventures on two places: Kochi and Kovalam.

We came to this decision while scanning over the itinerary we had created, which revealed a packed schedule - in transit every two or three days and spending over 50 hours sitting, standing or laying in a train.

Kochi

Kochi is an ancient port city in south-central Kerala, founded way back in the 14th century. It has a long history of trading with many countries from all over the Old World, including Portugal, Netherlands, China and Japan, which has over time created a distinct cosmopolitan culture unlike any other place in India.

Being well known around the world from of its valuable spice trade industry was probably a big reason why the Portuguese chose it as their gateway to colonisation in India, with occupation beginning in 1503. To this day you can still see the effects of colonisation in the old town, with European influences on architecture, art and religion visible everywhere.

Getting around

So you’ll probably want to stay in or near Fort Kochi (also referred to as the old town or Old Kochi). This is where most of the tourist attractions and some of the best restaurants are found.

If you heed my advice you’ll find that most places can easily be reached on foot. If you’re not into walking, cycling is a great way to get around the old town as the roads are pretty calm and most journeys should take no longer than 15 minutes.


A gorgeous little street in Old Kochi

There is a local bus network in Kochi that is apparently very good, but the tuk tuks are so cheap and convenient we just used them whenever we needed to go on a longer journey.

Things to do

You could probably visit most of the top attractions Fort Kochi has in a day. It’s worth staying a bit longer as the town itself has a nice vibe and there’s a great restaurant scene. Here are the highlights.

Elephant Festival

Entry: free. The day we arrived to Kochi our host told us about an elephant festival that would be happening nearby at 17:00. I don’t think this is an everyday occurrence, we just got lucky with the day we arrived.

We were excited with what we saw as this was our first time seeing elephants this close up and outside of a zoo. There was a short parade followed by traditional music and a ritual which ended with a blessing of the elephants.



Sadly the legs of these gentle giants were chained together and all three of them had a couple of men sitting or standing on their backs. At this time we weren’t aware of how serious and horrible elephant cruelty is in India and many other countries.

Looking back with this new information the whole event seemed a bit cruel and unfair. Who knows, maybe these ones were well cared for but evidence would suggest otherwise. Watch the video below and decide on the ethicality of such an event for yourself.



Chinese Fishing Nets

Entry: free. If you do a Google Image search for Kochi the most frequent image you will see as you scroll down is the iconic Chinese Fishing Nets at Fort Kochi Beach. Below is an example I grabbed from Google. Beautiful isn’t it?

Expectation. Source: Kerala Trips

If you hope to see the Chinese Fishing Nets looking remotely like this come at sunset. We went in the early afternoon and they were the pretty ugly, with rubbish strewn everywhere around them and that typical smell you get near a fish market. I’ll show you my pic but look away if you still want to go as it might turn you off!


Reality. Source: Me

Santa Cruz Cathedral Basilica

Entry: free. 2.3% of the population identifies as Christian, making it the third most followed religion in India, behind Hinduism (80%) and Islam (14%). It’s believed that Christianity was first introduced to India by Thomas the Apostle in 52 AD, but it began to spread more effectively in the 16th century when the Portuguese came and colonised.


Santa Cruz Cathedral Basilica

Indo-Portuguese Museum

Entry: Rs. 25. Established to showcase the Portuguese influence on Kochi and the surrounding areas, this is a small museum displaying mostly Christian relics and artefacts. We didn’t find it particularly interesting and didn’t stay long. It could be something to do if you have a lot of time to spare.

St. Francis Church

Entry: free. To look at, it’s just an ordinary no frills old church, badly in need of some maintenance, but looks don’t write history. Built in 1503, this is the oldest European church in India. Over the years it has changed hands several times between the Portuguese, Dutch and British as they battled for control over the city.


St. Francis Church. 📸 by Sarah

The explorer Vasco de Gama, who discovered the sea route from Europe to India in 1498, was buried here for 14 years before his remains were returned to Portugal. It’s historical and cultural significance was marked in 1923 when it was declared a protected monument.

Sitar and Tabla Performance

Entry: Rs. 200. A flyer advertising a sitar and tabla performance in Kerala Kathakali Centre caught our eye as we wandered the quaint streets of Old Kochi so we decided to check it out. We had absolutely no idea what a sitar and tabla were or what to expect.


Tablaist (left) and sitarist mid-performance

We loved it. The performance began at 20:00 and consisted of two talented musicians - one on sitar and the other on tabla - playing an intimate one hour set of hypnotising instrumental music. I think the small audience was in a trance as the only noises in the entire hour came from those beautiful instruments.


An old cannon in Vasco de Gama Square


A local park that becomes a cricket stadium in the evenings

Places to eat

Kochi has some mouth-wateringly good restaurants 🤤.

Qissa Café

I’ll admit, we’re not fan the biggest fans of an Indian breakfast. We always ended up getting some of our favourite Western breakfasts which can be easily found in tourist areas. It’s been five months and I still have dreams about the breakfast we had in Qissa.
📍 Near Private Bus Terminal, 18, KB Jacob Rd, Fort Kochi


In brunch heaven at Qissa Café. 📸 by Sarah

Farmer’s Café

We came here for dinner one night and shared a harbour masala (fish cooked in spicy gravy) and it was so so good. No pics because it was eaten so fast.
📍 682001, Rids Dale road, Next to the post office, Fort Kochi

Kovalam

We didn’t plan to do too much in Kovalam. Besides, there’s not really anything to do apart from chill at the beach which is exactly what we wanted. I was still trying to go from pale to slightly less pale and five days in sunny Kovalam is a good place to do just that.

It’s also a quick 20 minute drive to Trivandrum Airport, where we were due to fly to Sri Lanka from on March 6th. This tipped the balance in favour of Kovalam when we were deciding where to stay.

Getting around

Kovalam is a small town of about 8,000. As the only things of interest to tourists are the beach and lighthouse you should be able to reach most places within a five minute walk.

If you want to find some cheaper local restaurants or an ATM (there aren’t any on the tourist strip oddly enough) you will need to venture a couple of streets back up a steep hill, which could take you 15 minutes or more.

Things to do

Other than lounging on the beach, browsing the small gift shops and dining, there’s not a whole lot to do here, which is exactly what attracts people. It’s a popular holiday destination where foreign and domestic tourists as well as locals come and enjoy the beach, seafood and sunshine.

Kovalam Beach

Entry: free. Poular with locals, this is a really nice beach but it is always so busy, so if you’re looking for something a bit more peaceful you should head back to Goa. We had a great time here sunbathing on the beach and cooling off in the sea.


Locals flock to Kovalam Beach for sunset. 📸 by Sarah

Lighthouse Beach

Entry: free. This beach sits adjacent to Kovalam Beach and is very popular with foreign tourists, separated only by a tiny strip of land and rocks. It gets its name from Vizhinjam lighthouse, which sits elevated on a hill at the south end looking down on the beach.


Lighthouse Beach in the morning. 📸 by Sarah


Breakfast with a view. 📸 by Sarah

Vizhinjam Lighthouse

Entry: Rs. 25. Towering above the coconut palm trees at a height of 36 metres, this picturesque and iconic landmark dominates the Kovalam skyline. If you ask a kid to draw a lighthouse it would probably look just like this. It’s open to visitors, but at the time we were here it was closed for renovations.


Vizhinjam Lighthouse. 📸 by Sarah

Moving on

अलविदा. गुडबाय. വിട … Goodbye India! What an experience. What a month. What a country. Our only regret is that we didn’t give it enough time. Kerala alone deserves at least a couple of weeks if you want to explore all it has to offer.

This may be our final destination in India, but there’s still a few more posts to come. Next week (or the week after) I’ll show you a one minute highlights video that I made. See you then 😉.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000YriqAQH.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Month in India: Hampi</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-hampi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Month in India: Hampi" /><published>2018-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-hampi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-hampi">&lt;p&gt;Hampi is a small rural village in the south Indian state of Karnataka. Truth be told there’s not much happening in the village itself, but that’s not what you come to see. Things used to be very different in Hampi; this was once a wealthy and thriving city, which became the capital of the Vijayanagara Empire in the 14th century until 1565 when the empire was defeated and the city destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now a UNESCO World Heritage Site, Hampi is dotted with hundreds of Hindu temples, structures and monuments, all in varying states of ruin, over an area covering 26km². It is surrounded by a stunning and unusual natural landscape of sandstone boulder hills that stretch farther than the eye can see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-here&quot;&gt;Getting here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like everywhere else in this trip, we came here by train. Well, nearly. Hampi itself doesn’t have a train station, the nearest being a 30 minute drive away in Hosapete. Because the choice of accommodation in Hampi is pretty poor we decided to base ourselves from Hosapete and make a day trip to Hampi by tuk tuk. This also allowed us to be close to the train station for our 06:20 departure time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting here was easy; a short eight hour train ride from Goa (yes eight hours is short in India) had us there by midafternoon and 20 minutes later we were checked into our hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stuck this leg of our trip in between two visits to Goa as direct onward trave to Kochi (our next destination) from Hosapete was proving to be awkward and long. The &lt;strong&gt;shortest&lt;/strong&gt; train journey on this route is almost 26 hours, and that’s before you factor in the guaranteed delays that would probably drag that figure up to 29 or more. I love train travel, but no way am I staying on one for that long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of Hampi’s structures are together in clusters, so for the most part you can easily get around on foot. However, as Hampi is quite spread out, naturally so are some of its clusters, so you will probably need another mode of transport to cover the longer distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty easy to find a tuk tuk - there are plenty waiting close to the main attractions or parked in the shade of big trees to avoid the unforgiving heat from the sun, so we made use of their services once or twice. Bicycles are another way to get around and you can rent them in the village, but we decided it might be difficult to cycle in such high temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hampi&quot;&gt;Hampi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. We only had one full day to see Hampi so we decided to have an early(ish) start to make the most of it. We left our hotel at around 08:30 after filling up on a big breakfast and immediately spotted a tuk tuk waiting to greet his first customer of the day, and got to Hampi a little after 09:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/XF3eHTZ.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Joining the morning rush to Hampi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t want a tour guide herding us around like sheep to the same few places they show everyone and missing out on the chance to explore the place on our own, but we also wanted to understand what it is we are looking at and how to find our way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found a small Hampi guidebook book for sale in our hotel and bought it for around Rs. 150 (less than €2). This really came in handy as we could just pop it open at any time and read about everything on the spot. This let us to go at our own pace and for a fraction of the price of a tour guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s totally free to get in to Hampi and to see most of the ruins, which is pretty great. However, if you want to see some of the main attractions there is a fee of Rs. 500 (€6.28) for foreigners. Virupaksha Temple is only an additional Rs. 2 to go inside but we didn’t even bother as we were a little bit strapped for time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is an unbelievably fair price when you see that a one day pass for the not too dissimilar Angkor Archeological Park in Cambodia is €32. Angkor is amazing and all but there is no way that it’s five times better, and in some ways I actually preferred Hampi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/3VuLbvX.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Virupaksha Temple to the left, boulder hills to the right&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/0hUJaxY.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Stepped Tank used to collect and hold rainwater during the monsoon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/bOaySSA.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Elephant Stables was one of our favourite attractions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/XcsBkVh.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Kadalekalu Ganesha reminds me of Ancient Rome&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/gcsne8h.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;These tourists we met were in awe of what they were seeing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;matanga-hill&quot;&gt;Matanga Hill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ever decide to come put &lt;em&gt;Climb Matanga Hill&lt;/em&gt; on your &lt;em&gt;Things I must do in Hampi&lt;/em&gt; list. It is the highest point in all of Hampi so you truly get a unique viewpoint of this ancient city, and on a clear day you can see for miles around. It’s not very difficult to climb, but the heat and humidity of the day poses the greatest challenge to you making it to the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/1nLaESx.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Beginning the ascent of Matanga Hill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s one reason it is probably best to go earlier or later in the day, for sunrise or sunset. The other reason being the stunning views you will be rewarded with at these times. We started the ascent at around 11:00, just as the temperature was moving from very hot (32°C) to very very hot (34°C).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/X6jbkYb.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How about that for a view?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/3ntekB1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Okay, one last time. These are small… but the ones out there are far away&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The views from the summit of this giant hill of boulders were simply breathtaking. In the distance we could make out Virupaksha Temple, standing at 49 metres high but made to look 49 millimetres tall from up here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was just the time of day, but there was nobody else here except for us and Gareth from New Zealand who we met halfway up. No waiting for someone to take their selfies so we could walk past them before waiting for the next person to take their selfies so we could walk past them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/A7sDPRd.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Hey I think I can see my house from here!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, we felt that we didn’t give ourselves enough time here. I feel that there is unfinished business between me and Hampi, and I definitely want to return and take my sweet time to explore it all and soak everything in. Nonetheless, what a spectacular place. Go here. Do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to Goa after this, but I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/india/a-month-in-india-goa&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;already talked about that&lt;/a&gt;. So next we will be going to our final state (😞): Kerala. There’s plenty to see and do here, but we decided to slow it right down and limit our last week in India to two places - Kochi and Kovalam.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="india" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="hampi" /><category term="temple" /><summary type="html">Hampi is a small rural village in the south Indian state of Karnataka. Truth be told there’s not much happening in the village itself, but that’s not what you come to see. Things used to be very different in Hampi; this was once a wealthy and thriving city, which became the capital of the Vijayanagara Empire in the 14th century until 1565 when the empire was defeated and the city destroyed.

Now a UNESCO World Heritage Site, Hampi is dotted with hundreds of Hindu temples, structures and monuments, all in varying states of ruin, over an area covering 26km². It is surrounded by a stunning and unusual natural landscape of sandstone boulder hills that stretch farther than the eye can see.

Getting here

Like everywhere else in this trip, we came here by train. Well, nearly. Hampi itself doesn’t have a train station, the nearest being a 30 minute drive away in Hosapete. Because the choice of accommodation in Hampi is pretty poor we decided to base ourselves from Hosapete and make a day trip to Hampi by tuk tuk. This also allowed us to be close to the train station for our 06:20 departure time.

Getting here was easy; a short eight hour train ride from Goa (yes eight hours is short in India) had us there by midafternoon and 20 minutes later we were checked into our hotel.

We stuck this leg of our trip in between two visits to Goa as direct onward trave to Kochi (our next destination) from Hosapete was proving to be awkward and long. The shortest train journey on this route is almost 26 hours, and that’s before you factor in the guaranteed delays that would probably drag that figure up to 29 or more. I love train travel, but no way am I staying on one for that long.

Getting around

A lot of Hampi’s structures are together in clusters, so for the most part you can easily get around on foot. However, as Hampi is quite spread out, naturally so are some of its clusters, so you will probably need another mode of transport to cover the longer distances.

It’s pretty easy to find a tuk tuk - there are plenty waiting close to the main attractions or parked in the shade of big trees to avoid the unforgiving heat from the sun, so we made use of their services once or twice. Bicycles are another way to get around and you can rent them in the village, but we decided it might be difficult to cycle in such high temperatures.

Hampi

Entry: free. We only had one full day to see Hampi so we decided to have an early(ish) start to make the most of it. We left our hotel at around 08:30 after filling up on a big breakfast and immediately spotted a tuk tuk waiting to greet his first customer of the day, and got to Hampi a little after 09:00.


Joining the morning rush to Hampi

We didn’t want a tour guide herding us around like sheep to the same few places they show everyone and missing out on the chance to explore the place on our own, but we also wanted to understand what it is we are looking at and how to find our way around.

We found a small Hampi guidebook book for sale in our hotel and bought it for around Rs. 150 (less than €2). This really came in handy as we could just pop it open at any time and read about everything on the spot. This let us to go at our own pace and for a fraction of the price of a tour guide.

It’s totally free to get in to Hampi and to see most of the ruins, which is pretty great. However, if you want to see some of the main attractions there is a fee of Rs. 500 (€6.28) for foreigners. Virupaksha Temple is only an additional Rs. 2 to go inside but we didn’t even bother as we were a little bit strapped for time.

That is an unbelievably fair price when you see that a one day pass for the not too dissimilar Angkor Archeological Park in Cambodia is €32. Angkor is amazing and all but there is no way that it’s five times better, and in some ways I actually preferred Hampi.


Virupaksha Temple to the left, boulder hills to the right


Stepped Tank used to collect and hold rainwater during the monsoon


The Elephant Stables was one of our favourite attractions


Kadalekalu Ganesha reminds me of Ancient Rome


These tourists we met were in awe of what they were seeing

Matanga Hill

If you ever decide to come put Climb Matanga Hill on your Things I must do in Hampi list. It is the highest point in all of Hampi so you truly get a unique viewpoint of this ancient city, and on a clear day you can see for miles around. It’s not very difficult to climb, but the heat and humidity of the day poses the greatest challenge to you making it to the top.


Beginning the ascent of Matanga Hill

That’s one reason it is probably best to go earlier or later in the day, for sunrise or sunset. The other reason being the stunning views you will be rewarded with at these times. We started the ascent at around 11:00, just as the temperature was moving from very hot (32°C) to very very hot (34°C).


How about that for a view?


Okay, one last time. These are small… but the ones out there are far away

The views from the summit of this giant hill of boulders were simply breathtaking. In the distance we could make out Virupaksha Temple, standing at 49 metres high but made to look 49 millimetres tall from up here.

Maybe it was just the time of day, but there was nobody else here except for us and Gareth from New Zealand who we met halfway up. No waiting for someone to take their selfies so we could walk past them before waiting for the next person to take their selfies so we could walk past them.


“Hey I think I can see my house from here!”

Moving on

Once again, we felt that we didn’t give ourselves enough time here. I feel that there is unfinished business between me and Hampi, and I definitely want to return and take my sweet time to explore it all and soak everything in. Nonetheless, what a spectacular place. Go here. Do it.

Back to Goa after this, but I’ve already talked about that. So next we will be going to our final state (😞): Kerala. There’s plenty to see and do here, but we decided to slow it right down and limit our last week in India to two places - Kochi and Kovalam.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:40000hUJaxY.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Month in India: Goa</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-goa" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Month in India: Goa" /><published>2018-07-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-goa</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-goa">&lt;p&gt;Fifteen days after we touched Indian soil for the first time, our arrival to Goa marked the halfway point in our one month tour of India. It also marked a halfway point in other ways: crossing the line from northern to southern India also brought a change in climate, food and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goa’s biggest attraction is its beaches and the atmosphere that comes with it. The entire state’s population is less than two million, which is partly made up by its many villages and towns hugging the coastline. You will be spoilt with all the choices really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a party scene with crowds of foreign tourists, water sports and never ending beach parties, then North Goa is for you. In South Goa you can find a much more laid-back atmosphere with small villages, deserted beaches and delicious food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to split our trip to Goa into two parts, so that we could leave in between to visit Hampi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arrosim&quot;&gt;Arrosim&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first part of this trip we stayed a twenty minute drive away from Vasco de Gama (Goa’s main town) in Arrosim. This sleepy village did not have much going on except for a few small shops and seemed completely unaffected by tourism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fifteen minute walk from here, down a small road and past a couple of quiet resorts will see you arrive at Arrosim Beach. Our first thoughts when we saw it were how vast and empty it was. Perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/vUACEFw.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A tiny snake we found at the entrance to Arrosim beach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the entrance to the beach there is a restaurant called &lt;em&gt;Star fish beach shack&lt;/em&gt;. We ate here on both days as there weren’t many options in the area, but also because of the great seafood, sound owners and free sunbeds for customers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/HKfubbR.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fresh red snapper and chips from Star fish beach shack&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/bgQwh9y.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sunsets at Arrosim beach are the best that I have seen anywhere. It’s easy to get a front row seat and watch as the sun gradually changes to a burning shade of red, before disappearing into the Arabian Sea directly in front of you, bringing daytime with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/u6FpEYv.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The sun preparing to set at Arrosim beach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-we-stayed&quot;&gt;Where we stayed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stayed in an Airbnb just outside of Arrosim village and only a ten minute walk to the beach. It was a great place to stay and the host Celiano was really nice. We chatted for a good while and he gave us some advice that made the rest of our travels in India a little bit easier. Here’s a link to his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/12144036?s=51&quot;&gt;Airbnb page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;agonda&quot;&gt;Agonda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we came back from Hampi we headed to another village in South Goa called Agonda, 50km south of Arrosim. This is a large village that has embraced tourism and is buzzing with activity from its multiple bars, restaurants, shops and the beach which is lined with resorts ranging in style from basic to luxurious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/JRpT5Vd.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Agonda Beach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with all of the people around, the beach never seemed to get very busy. This is probably helped by the fact that it is both wide and &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; long. Agonda was a winner for us, it’s really nice and clean with plenty of places to eat, drink and sleep only metres away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-we-stayed-1&quot;&gt;Where we stayed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stayed in a resort which sits right on the north part of the beach called &lt;a href=&quot;http://velvetsunset.com&quot;&gt;Velvet Sunset&lt;/a&gt;. This place was great; the staff were really helpful and it has a great restaurant and bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the porch of our simple wooden hut you could see the ocean. We went with the cheapest option available when booking our room, which got us a fan and cold, salty shower!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://velvetsunset.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/113601347.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What we could have gotten if we splashed out!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to get to most places in Goa from the railway station is by taxi. There are local buses, but when you’ve just gotten off an eight hour overnight train you just want to get out of transit as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to save money on a taxi is to look out for other travellers who are going to the same area as you so you can share the fare. This is especially easy in Goa as the majority of people are going to the same few places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get to your village or town you will easily be able to walk everywhere as the places are usually quite small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our only regret about Goa is that we didn’t give ourselves more time here. We loved it and easily could have stayed for another week or more just living a simple beach life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So technically we went to Kerala after Goa, but remember we left in the middle for a few days to visit Hampi, an ancient city which was once the capital of the Vijayanagara Empire and is now a UNESCO World Heritage Site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This magnificent site covering an area of 26km² is dotted with ruined temples and structures which will leave you inspired by what people were able to build hundreds of years ago and in awe of the unique natural landscape that surrounds it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="india" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="goa" /><summary type="html">Fifteen days after we touched Indian soil for the first time, our arrival to Goa marked the halfway point in our one month tour of India. It also marked a halfway point in other ways: crossing the line from northern to southern India also brought a change in climate, food and cultures.

Goa’s biggest attraction is its beaches and the atmosphere that comes with it. The entire state’s population is less than two million, which is partly made up by its many villages and towns hugging the coastline. You will be spoilt with all the choices really.

If you are looking for a party scene with crowds of foreign tourists, water sports and never ending beach parties, then North Goa is for you. In South Goa you can find a much more laid-back atmosphere with small villages, deserted beaches and delicious food.

We decided to split our trip to Goa into two parts, so that we could leave in between to visit Hampi.

Arrosim

For the first part of this trip we stayed a twenty minute drive away from Vasco de Gama (Goa’s main town) in Arrosim. This sleepy village did not have much going on except for a few small shops and seemed completely unaffected by tourism.

A fifteen minute walk from here, down a small road and past a couple of quiet resorts will see you arrive at Arrosim Beach. Our first thoughts when we saw it were how vast and empty it was. Perfect.


A tiny snake we found at the entrance to Arrosim beach

At the entrance to the beach there is a restaurant called Star fish beach shack. We ate here on both days as there weren’t many options in the area, but also because of the great seafood, sound owners and free sunbeds for customers!


Fresh red snapper and chips from Star fish beach shack



The sunsets at Arrosim beach are the best that I have seen anywhere. It’s easy to get a front row seat and watch as the sun gradually changes to a burning shade of red, before disappearing into the Arabian Sea directly in front of you, bringing daytime with it.


The sun preparing to set at Arrosim beach

Where we stayed

We stayed in an Airbnb just outside of Arrosim village and only a ten minute walk to the beach. It was a great place to stay and the host Celiano was really nice. We chatted for a good while and he gave us some advice that made the rest of our travels in India a little bit easier. Here’s a link to his Airbnb page.

Agonda

After we came back from Hampi we headed to another village in South Goa called Agonda, 50km south of Arrosim. This is a large village that has embraced tourism and is buzzing with activity from its multiple bars, restaurants, shops and the beach which is lined with resorts ranging in style from basic to luxurious.


Agonda Beach

Even with all of the people around, the beach never seemed to get very busy. This is probably helped by the fact that it is both wide and really long. Agonda was a winner for us, it’s really nice and clean with plenty of places to eat, drink and sleep only metres away.

Where we stayed

We stayed in a resort which sits right on the north part of the beach called Velvet Sunset. This place was great; the staff were really helpful and it has a great restaurant and bar.

From the porch of our simple wooden hut you could see the ocean. We went with the cheapest option available when booking our room, which got us a fan and cold, salty shower!


What we could have gotten if we splashed out!

Getting around

The best way to get to most places in Goa from the railway station is by taxi. There are local buses, but when you’ve just gotten off an eight hour overnight train you just want to get out of transit as quickly as possible.

One way to save money on a taxi is to look out for other travellers who are going to the same area as you so you can share the fare. This is especially easy in Goa as the majority of people are going to the same few places.

Once you get to your village or town you will easily be able to walk everywhere as the places are usually quite small.

Moving on

Our only regret about Goa is that we didn’t give ourselves more time here. We loved it and easily could have stayed for another week or more just living a simple beach life.

So technically we went to Kerala after Goa, but remember we left in the middle for a few days to visit Hampi, an ancient city which was once the capital of the Vijayanagara Empire and is now a UNESCO World Heritage Site.

This magnificent site covering an area of 26km² is dotted with ruined temples and structures which will leave you inspired by what people were able to build hundreds of years ago and in awe of the unique natural landscape that surrounds it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000JRpT5Vd.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Month in India: Mumbai</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-mumbai" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Month in India: Mumbai" /><published>2018-07-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-mumbai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-mumbai">&lt;p&gt;Mumbai holds the title of being India’s largest city, with an estimated population of around 24 million. The commercial centre of India, home to Asia’s largest slum, the world’s most expensive home and Bollywood; this is a city of extremes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up staying five nights here. This seems like a lot (and it is), but it was just the awkward timings of our arrival and departure that caused this. We flew from Udaipur and arrived at about 20:00 on 15th February and our onward train was at 05:00 on 20th February. In reality we had four full days to explore the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four days was probably still too much time to spend here - we didn’t really enjoy it too much. Why? I can’t quite put my finger on it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was the lack of cheap and quality accommodation which pushed us a thirty minute drive away from the buzz of Colaba district. Maybe it was the fact we had already been to Delhi so the thrill and culture shock of experiencing a city of this size wasn’t there anymore. Coming from the beauty and charm of Udaipur probably didn’t hour expectations either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was just our experience though…it could be completely different for you. I think if we forked out that extra cash to stay in the Colaba district our experience would have been much more positive. It was from this point on that we decided that the most important thing to consider when booking accommodation is its location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever money we saved by choosing a cheaper place to stay was probably negated by those long taxi drives (and our mediocre negotiating skills) to and from our hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuk tuks are banned from Central Mumbai, so you will probably be riding in taxis more often here. There is a metro but it is relatively new and is actively being expanded. Honestly if you stay in the Colaba district you should be able to walk to most places. We usually got a taxi to here and then walked everywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taxi&quot;&gt;Taxi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used taxis for all of our long distance journeys in the city. Like everywhere in India, it’s rare to find a taxi using a meter so know the standard fares and have an idea of how much your journey should cost. We used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.numbeo.com/taxi-fare/in/Mumbai&quot;&gt;this fare calculator from Numbeo&lt;/a&gt; to do just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uberola&quot;&gt;Uber/Ola&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have Internet access you should definitely use one of these ride-sharing services for the best deal. At this point we still hadn’t gotten sorted with a working Indian SIM card, so were still working it the old fashioned way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;metro&quot;&gt;Metro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said, the Mumbai Metro network is still a work in progress and is not nearly as expansive as the one in Delhi. We used it a couple of times and found it be a very efficient and easy way to get across the city, avoiding all those messy traffic jams. Unlike the Delhi Metro, there is no tourist day pass so you will be paying on a journey by journey basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;walking&quot;&gt;Walking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not suggesting that you can walk to anywhere in the city (far from it), but if you are in the right areas walking in Mumbai is a breeze. This is in part thanks to an extremely positive change introduced in late 2017 which banned kiosks, parked (and moving) vehicles and other annoying obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-to-do&quot;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gateway-of-india&quot;&gt;Gateway of India&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. Built during the colonial era to commemorate the visit of King George V in 1911, this is an impressive structure. You can’t get close to it or walk under though, which was a bit disappointing. I wonder will they contruct a similar gateway to commemorate our visit? 😜&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/QZg6zVg.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My uninspiring shot of the Gateway of India&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chhatrapati-shivaji-maharaj-vastu-sangrahalaya&quot;&gt;Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Vastu Sangrahalaya&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs 300&lt;/em&gt;. Please don’t ask me to pronounce that. Thankfully you can refer to it by its abbreviation, CSMVS. This is the main museum in Mumbai, displaying around 50,000 art, history and archeological artefacts. This is too much for me as I get tired of museums after about two hours, so we didn’t stick around to see them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/zUvnyOs.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Vastu Sangrahalaya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dharavi&quot;&gt;Dharavi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting Asia’s biggest slum was our favourite activity in Mumbai. On the face of it, most people would consider this a bit unethical. We were like that too, but a bit of research goes a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tour company we chose, &lt;a href=&quot;http://realitytoursandtravel.com/dharavi-tour.php&quot;&gt;Reality Tours &amp;amp; Travel&lt;/a&gt;, was set up with the aim of destigmatizing the world’s view on this 2.1 km² area that houses one million of Mumbai’s inhabitants. Our guide Tavrej lives in Dharavi, and he really was amazing in helping to achieve the vision of educating us about Mumbai’s beating heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5564/31364575501_92e14a9580_b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rooftop View&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Rooftop view of Dharavi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of Dharavi’s citizens do not want to leave this place they call home, despite past government efforts to help relocate them. Any why would they? They have a hospital, schools, markets, mosques, temples and many thriving industries that have a combined annual turnover of approximately $665 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To respect the locals’ privacy we were requested not to take photographs during the tour. Instead, they provided us with a collection of photos from around Dharavi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5573/31480292685_d1f44de6a6_b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paint Barrels Recycling&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Recycling paint barrels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Mumbai wasn’t for us. I think we just wanted to get out of the cities. Luckily for us, our next destination would be as far removed from big city life as you can imagine. Goa is a blend of Indian and Portuguese cultures: with small villages, quiet beaches, fresh seafood and a laid-back atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="india" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="mumbai" /><summary type="html">Mumbai holds the title of being India’s largest city, with an estimated population of around 24 million. The commercial centre of India, home to Asia’s largest slum, the world’s most expensive home and Bollywood; this is a city of extremes.

We ended up staying five nights here. This seems like a lot (and it is), but it was just the awkward timings of our arrival and departure that caused this. We flew from Udaipur and arrived at about 20:00 on 15th February and our onward train was at 05:00 on 20th February. In reality we had four full days to explore the city.

Four days was probably still too much time to spend here - we didn’t really enjoy it too much. Why? I can’t quite put my finger on it…

Maybe it was the lack of cheap and quality accommodation which pushed us a thirty minute drive away from the buzz of Colaba district. Maybe it was the fact we had already been to Delhi so the thrill and culture shock of experiencing a city of this size wasn’t there anymore. Coming from the beauty and charm of Udaipur probably didn’t hour expectations either.

This was just our experience though…it could be completely different for you. I think if we forked out that extra cash to stay in the Colaba district our experience would have been much more positive. It was from this point on that we decided that the most important thing to consider when booking accommodation is its location.

Whatever money we saved by choosing a cheaper place to stay was probably negated by those long taxi drives (and our mediocre negotiating skills) to and from our hotel.

Getting around

Tuk tuks are banned from Central Mumbai, so you will probably be riding in taxis more often here. There is a metro but it is relatively new and is actively being expanded. Honestly if you stay in the Colaba district you should be able to walk to most places. We usually got a taxi to here and then walked everywhere else.

Taxi

We used taxis for all of our long distance journeys in the city. Like everywhere in India, it’s rare to find a taxi using a meter so know the standard fares and have an idea of how much your journey should cost. We used this fare calculator from Numbeo to do just that.

Uber/Ola

If you have Internet access you should definitely use one of these ride-sharing services for the best deal. At this point we still hadn’t gotten sorted with a working Indian SIM card, so were still working it the old fashioned way.

Metro

As I’ve said, the Mumbai Metro network is still a work in progress and is not nearly as expansive as the one in Delhi. We used it a couple of times and found it be a very efficient and easy way to get across the city, avoiding all those messy traffic jams. Unlike the Delhi Metro, there is no tourist day pass so you will be paying on a journey by journey basis.

Walking

Now I’m not suggesting that you can walk to anywhere in the city (far from it), but if you are in the right areas walking in Mumbai is a breeze. This is in part thanks to an extremely positive change introduced in late 2017 which banned kiosks, parked (and moving) vehicles and other annoying obstacles.

Things to do

Gateway of India

Entry: free. Built during the colonial era to commemorate the visit of King George V in 1911, this is an impressive structure. You can’t get close to it or walk under though, which was a bit disappointing. I wonder will they contruct a similar gateway to commemorate our visit? 😜


My uninspiring shot of the Gateway of India

Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Vastu Sangrahalaya

Entry: Rs 300. Please don’t ask me to pronounce that. Thankfully you can refer to it by its abbreviation, CSMVS. This is the main museum in Mumbai, displaying around 50,000 art, history and archeological artefacts. This is too much for me as I get tired of museums after about two hours, so we didn’t stick around to see them all.


Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Vastu Sangrahalaya

Dharavi

Visiting Asia’s biggest slum was our favourite activity in Mumbai. On the face of it, most people would consider this a bit unethical. We were like that too, but a bit of research goes a long way.

The tour company we chose, Reality Tours &amp;amp; Travel, was set up with the aim of destigmatizing the world’s view on this 2.1 km² area that houses one million of Mumbai’s inhabitants. Our guide Tavrej lives in Dharavi, and he really was amazing in helping to achieve the vision of educating us about Mumbai’s beating heart.


Rooftop view of Dharavi

The majority of Dharavi’s citizens do not want to leave this place they call home, despite past government efforts to help relocate them. Any why would they? They have a hospital, schools, markets, mosques, temples and many thriving industries that have a combined annual turnover of approximately $665 million.

To respect the locals’ privacy we were requested not to take photographs during the tour. Instead, they provided us with a collection of photos from around Dharavi.


Recycling paint barrels

Moving on

So, Mumbai wasn’t for us. I think we just wanted to get out of the cities. Luckily for us, our next destination would be as far removed from big city life as you can imagine. Goa is a blend of Indian and Portuguese cultures: with small villages, quiet beaches, fresh seafood and a laid-back atmosphere.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000zUvnyOs.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Month in India: Udaipur</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-udaipur" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Month in India: Udaipur" /><published>2018-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-udaipur</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-udaipur">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/travel/india/a-month-in-india-agra&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Last week&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about our time in Agra and our visit to the Taj Mahal. In this post we head west to Udaipur, in the desert state of Rajasthan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Udaipur is a &lt;em&gt;must visit&lt;/em&gt; if you travel to India. It is sometimes called the “White City” because of the colour of the buildings in the old city. It s also known as the “City of Lakes” because of its several artificial lakes. I’ve seen it called the “Venice of the East” because of these lakes, but this title &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_places_called_Venice_of_the_East&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;seems to be used for any city with a bit of water&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent a total of four days here, and in that short period we fell in love with the charming aura of this old city. The people, mouth watering food, narrow winding streets, picturesque lakes, the beautiful palaces and temples all created a special atmosphere like nowhere else in India (that we visited).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are staying in the old city (which you should) you can reach most places by foot pretty easily. As confusing and unplanned as the streets seemed we never managed to get lost. Most streets are pedestrian friendly, helped by the fact that they are narrow; rendering them unsuitable to anything other than people, bikes and cows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/RjL0HL7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Let’s see where this street leads to&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/QIJNxnt.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most activities and sights of interest are located in and around the old city. If you need to go further afield to the new city or if you’re just tired of walking around you can easily find a tuk tuk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We walked nearly everywhere in Udaipur. Most streets and alleys have something interesting that make them worth walking down. Many have some form of street art; styles varied from your typical modern street “graffiti” to some traditional Rajput-style murals like in the picture below. Other than that you will see animals chilling in the sun or street vendors plying their trade throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/EJ6NLse.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You will find many murals like this hidden all around the old city&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/ljP4uSQ.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/VWbeAsv.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In India, cows rule&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/5MPdjdk.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This is the usual cause of a traffic jam here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/wlebbY9.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-we-stayed&quot;&gt;Where we stayed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stayed in a guesthouse called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mewargarhpalace.co.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mewargarh Palace&lt;/a&gt; for our three nights in Udaipur. We got a private ensuite bedroom for Rs 700 (€8.84)/night. Bargain! And no, we didn’t have to compromise on quality for that price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of the nicest places we stayed in during this trip! It was clean, comfortable, the owners were really friendly and the rooftop restaurant served good food with a view. However, there were two downsides to staying here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We both were woken up a few times every night because of dogs in the area barking constantly. There is also a mosque nearby and they like to convene for their daily prayers at dawn, which meant that we were awake very early every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/QUWME0E.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The view from Mewargarh Palace’s rooftop restaurant&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these downsides were not the fault of the guesthouse and you should kind of expect noises like this if you’re staying in a city. So yes, I would definitely recommend staying here… just be to sure to bring a good pair of earplugs 👍.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-to-do&quot;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;city-palace&quot;&gt;City Palace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs 500&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t worry, if you want to just visit the grounds of the City Palace it’s free. Go inside however and you will get the chance to witness where the Mewar dynasty ruled from for 400 years and see how they lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/8VqBe03.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The view of City Palace from outside&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/gP3G6gm.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking down at Lake Pichola from inside City Palace&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/So7B1Ho.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jagdish-temple&quot;&gt;Jagdish Temple&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. This large Hindu temple located in the heart of the old city has been host to continuous worship since 1651. Its grey stone surface, which peaks at 24 metres, is covered with intricate Hindu carvings and is supported by many beautifully carved pillars.
&lt;br /&gt;When we were here there was catchy religious music and song coming from inside, which we stayed to watch and enjoy for a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-2&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/OO9s7Bp.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Detailed carvings on one side of Jagdish Temple&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;macchla-hill&quot;&gt;Macchla Hill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. You can climb it for free, but we had already done a lot of walking this day so decided to pay Rs 300 each to take a cable car to the top of Machhala Hill, home to the renowned Karni Mata Temple. We didn’t visit the temple but did come for the spectacular views of Udaipur and its many lakes. We came during the day but I can imagine that the view would be particularly special at sunset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/dAiiLzB.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;From the top of Machhla Hill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/dCBtbtY.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;An unobstructed view of the city from Machhla Hill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gangaur-ghat&quot;&gt;Gangaur Ghat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: free&lt;/em&gt;. This is a nice place to spend some time in the evening. Just sit on the steps leading down to the water and watch the boats go by or the people coming to socialise after their long day at work or school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/wm6h6cr.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sarah making friends at Gangaur Ghat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dharohar-folk-dance&quot;&gt;Dharohar Folk Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs 150&lt;/em&gt;. If you want to get a glimpse of Rajasthani heritage this show is for you. Hosted in Bagore-ki-Haveli, the performance itself is a rich myriad of folk dances, music, bright colours and a puppet show, which lasts about one hour. This is an extremely popular show which we really enjoyed and tickets usually sell out, so it’s advised to get there eary to avoid disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/3l2zLKV.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;One of the performances during a one hour long folk show&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were sad to leave Udaipur, but after four days here it was time to move on. Next we travel to Mumbai, India’s largest city. Home to the world’s most expensive home, the largest slum in Asia and Bollywood; this is a city of extremes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="india" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="udaipur" /><category term="rajasthan" /><summary type="html">Last week, I talked about our time in Agra and our visit to the Taj Mahal. In this post we head west to Udaipur, in the desert state of Rajasthan.

Udaipur is a must visit if you travel to India. It is sometimes called the “White City” because of the colour of the buildings in the old city. It s also known as the “City of Lakes” because of its several artificial lakes. I’ve seen it called the “Venice of the East” because of these lakes, but this title seems to be used for any city with a bit of water.

We spent a total of four days here, and in that short period we fell in love with the charming aura of this old city. The people, mouth watering food, narrow winding streets, picturesque lakes, the beautiful palaces and temples all created a special atmosphere like nowhere else in India (that we visited).

Getting around

If you are staying in the old city (which you should) you can reach most places by foot pretty easily. As confusing and unplanned as the streets seemed we never managed to get lost. Most streets are pedestrian friendly, helped by the fact that they are narrow; rendering them unsuitable to anything other than people, bikes and cows.


Let’s see where this street leads to



Most activities and sights of interest are located in and around the old city. If you need to go further afield to the new city or if you’re just tired of walking around you can easily find a tuk tuk.

We walked nearly everywhere in Udaipur. Most streets and alleys have something interesting that make them worth walking down. Many have some form of street art; styles varied from your typical modern street “graffiti” to some traditional Rajput-style murals like in the picture below. Other than that you will see animals chilling in the sun or street vendors plying their trade throughout the day.


You will find many murals like this hidden all around the old city




In India, cows rule


This is the usual cause of a traffic jam here



Where we stayed

We stayed in a guesthouse called Mewargarh Palace for our three nights in Udaipur. We got a private ensuite bedroom for Rs 700 (€8.84)/night. Bargain! And no, we didn’t have to compromise on quality for that price.

This was one of the nicest places we stayed in during this trip! It was clean, comfortable, the owners were really friendly and the rooftop restaurant served good food with a view. However, there were two downsides to staying here.

We both were woken up a few times every night because of dogs in the area barking constantly. There is also a mosque nearby and they like to convene for their daily prayers at dawn, which meant that we were awake very early every day.


The view from Mewargarh Palace’s rooftop restaurant

Both of these downsides were not the fault of the guesthouse and you should kind of expect noises like this if you’re staying in a city. So yes, I would definitely recommend staying here… just be to sure to bring a good pair of earplugs 👍.

Things to do

City Palace

Entry: Rs 500. Don’t worry, if you want to just visit the grounds of the City Palace it’s free. Go inside however and you will get the chance to witness where the Mewar dynasty ruled from for 400 years and see how they lived.


The view of City Palace from outside


Looking down at Lake Pichola from inside City Palace



Jagdish Temple

Entry: free. This large Hindu temple located in the heart of the old city has been host to continuous worship since 1651. Its grey stone surface, which peaks at 24 metres, is covered with intricate Hindu carvings and is supported by many beautifully carved pillars.
When we were here there was catchy religious music and song coming from inside, which we stayed to watch and enjoy for a few minutes.


Detailed carvings on one side of Jagdish Temple

Macchla Hill

Entry: free. You can climb it for free, but we had already done a lot of walking this day so decided to pay Rs 300 each to take a cable car to the top of Machhala Hill, home to the renowned Karni Mata Temple. We didn’t visit the temple but did come for the spectacular views of Udaipur and its many lakes. We came during the day but I can imagine that the view would be particularly special at sunset.


From the top of Machhla Hill


An unobstructed view of the city from Machhla Hill

Gangaur Ghat

Entry: free. This is a nice place to spend some time in the evening. Just sit on the steps leading down to the water and watch the boats go by or the people coming to socialise after their long day at work or school.


Sarah making friends at Gangaur Ghat

Dharohar Folk Dance

Entry: Rs 150. If you want to get a glimpse of Rajasthani heritage this show is for you. Hosted in Bagore-ki-Haveli, the performance itself is a rich myriad of folk dances, music, bright colours and a puppet show, which lasts about one hour. This is an extremely popular show which we really enjoyed and tickets usually sell out, so it’s advised to get there eary to avoid disappointment.


One of the performances during a one hour long folk show

Moving on

We were sad to leave Udaipur, but after four days here it was time to move on. Next we travel to Mumbai, India’s largest city. Home to the world’s most expensive home, the largest slum in Asia and Bollywood; this is a city of extremes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000dAiiLzB.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">One Month in India: Agra</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-agra" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Month in India: Agra" /><published>2018-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-agra</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/travel/india/a-month-in-india-agra">&lt;p&gt;When people visit Agra - the second stop on India’s Golden Triangle - they are not coming to see the city that 1.6 million people call home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year up to eight million people travel from all over the world to see it. A UNESCO World Heritage Site and one of the New7Wonders of the World, your goldfish has probably heard of the Taj Mahal. It is the most &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt; place I have been to in my entire life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-here&quot;&gt;Getting here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Delhi, Agra takes just over three hours by train, covering some 206 kilometres. This was to be our first of several train rides in India, and it was something we were both nervous and excited for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found it &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; difficult to even reach a stage where we could purchase our tickets online, and were about to look into alternative modes of transport when we finally came up with a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously…it took over a month to register on the official train reservation website. I even went to the length of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PhelanEnda/status/951129157370630145&quot;&gt;contacting the Minister of Railways&lt;/a&gt;, which lead nowhere. I will explain what we did to resolve the issue in depth another time, but if you need help more urgently &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt; and I’ll try to help you out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/Z5TGJ3c.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My top bunk in a 3AC carriage going from Delhi to Agra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trains in India do not have any digital display or voice-over telling you when to get off and you can’t rely on the schedule as the train will be running late more often than not. Use an app or website like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.railyatri.in/&quot;&gt;RailYatri&lt;/a&gt; which will show you the live running status of your train. You will be completely lost without it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pulled in to Agra Cantt railway station about an hour late. As we step off the train onto the platform we hear cries of “taxi! taxi!” directed at us. We learned that in order to get the best deal, you should avoid people like this and instead go out of the station and look for a taxi or tuk tuk by yourself.
It turns out that this station only has one prepaid taxi booth with fixed prices, so it’s the same price regardless of who you go with. It was expensive, so if you have internet you should use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.olacabs.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ola&lt;/a&gt; for a better deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-around&quot;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only places in Agra you will probably visit are the Taj Mahal and Agra Fort (another UNESCO World Heritage Site). For this the best way to get around is by tuk tuk. You can find them on every corner, now it’s up to you to negotiate a good deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sightseeing&quot;&gt;Sightseeing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three UNESCO World Heritage Sites in Agra, I’ve mentioned two. The third, Fatehpur Sikri, is located 40 kilometres outside of the city, so we didn’t make it there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taj-mahal&quot;&gt;Taj Mahal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs 1000&lt;/em&gt;. We decided to pry ourselves prematurely from the comfort of our bed at 04:00 to be here for sunrise. We found a tuk tuk pretty easily and arrived at the Taj Mahal entrance at about 05:00 to find a long queue ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nooo!&lt;/em&gt; We thought we were going to miss sunrise. A tour guide hovering near the queue told us that we can skip it if we get a guide. Not wanting to miss what we had gotten up so early for, we didn’t hesitate in saying yes. We hopped the barrier right in front of the queue as they all watched us, probably thinking &lt;em&gt;cunts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next obstacle: baggage checks. We weren’t aware of the many &lt;em&gt;Dos&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Donts&lt;/em&gt; for coming here, other than the strict dress code. We each had a book and I had a GoPro selfie stick which security were &lt;em&gt;convinced&lt;/em&gt; was a tripod - two forbidden items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily our guide worked his charm on the guards and we were allowed to bring them in on condition that they stayed in our bags. So yeah, read the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tajmahal.gov.in/do%26nots.html&quot;&gt;list of do’s and dont’s&lt;/a&gt; provided by the Department of Tourism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We probably would have made it into the palace grounds in time for sunrise, but having a guide was useful because he brought us to the best place to watch the sun rising over the palace. If you want to see it, head towards the mosque situated to the left of the Taj Mahal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/OITOh71.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Taj Mahal stands out proudly from the thick morning fog&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can probably see from the picture above there is another benefit of coming this early…very few people around! Come at noon and the paths either side of the water will be crowded with tourists, ruining that perfect shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/X9jVq46.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What a sight: the sun rising from behind the Taj Mahal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We parted ways with our guide after about two hours. If you have the money, hiring a guide is a good idea as you will learn some things you may not have known about this iconic place without some research. Be sure to only hire an approved guide who show their official identity cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/GdSiaBE.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Our tour guide knew all the best places to take photos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found a seat, sat and just watched for a little while. Watched the crowds slowly thicken and the noise level increase, the sun continue to rise high into the sky, and the shifting colours of the Taj Mahal’s marble surface, influenced by the changing colour of the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/vabHNCu.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This photo makes you realise how big the Taj Mahal is&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once outside the palace grounds you will notice something unusual for India (or most places for that matter). It’s quiet. Polluting vehicles are not allowed within 500 metres of the Taj Mahal, all you will see here are bicycles and electric vehicles. This is a great idea as you really notice the serenity from within the palace grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area outside the palace walls is lined with restaurants and gifts shops, ready to serve the happy tourists enlightened by their visit to the Taj Mahal. Our guide highly recommended a restaurant called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g297683-d804436-Reviews-Joney_s_Place-Agra_Agra_District_Uttar_Pradesh.html?m=19905&quot;&gt;Joney’s place&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We walked around but couldn’t find it (and didn’t have a working SIM card to use Google Maps) so I can’t attest to it’s deliciousness, but we did meet someone later in our trip who said he came here twice in the same day it was so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;agra-fort&quot;&gt;Agra Fort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entry: Rs 550&lt;/em&gt;. Just 2.5 kilometres away, Agra Fort is worth the short journey by tuk tuk. It was the residence of the Mughal Dynasty until 1638, before they moved to Delhi because of soaring rent prices and expensive child care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/1PjQGFj.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;By 11:00am the entrance to Agra Fort was already bustling with tourists&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the grounds you will find more impressive architecture and well maintained gardens. You might come across two maintenance workers offering you the chance to hold and feed some squirrels. Be aware that they will demand money, but only &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; you have fed and held them. I’m hesitant to call it a scam because most people will cop this before accepting the offer. I am not most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/0csji0R.jpg&quot; class=&quot;post-image post-image-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Best friends forever&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-on&quot;&gt;Moving on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s Agra done. Next week I’ll tell you about Udaipur (known as the “White City”) in the state of Rajasthan. This place is really special and so relaxed compared to Delhi and Agra, and was one of our favourite places in all of India.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="india" /><category term="travel" /><category term="backpacking" /><category term="agra" /><category term="tajmahal" /><summary type="html">When people visit Agra - the second stop on India’s Golden Triangle - they are not coming to see the city that 1.6 million people call home.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000OITOh71.jpg" /></entry></feed>
